Ah, the shrinking brain. A conundrum of
age. Mine might disappear soon
considering its starting point. I'll
just be all hollow up here unless there
is something that could prevent that
from happening like this diet and these
foods that we'll discuss. We'll go over
the brain shrinking different diets and
the best diet among the three for
preventing this brain shrinking
phenomenon. Let's discuss. In a
randomized control trial, researchers
assigned almost 300 participants to one
of three diets. A healthy dietary
guidelines diet called the HDG group.
That's their gang name to. This diet was
just a simple standard counseling to
consume a balanced diet. Nothing too
special other than avoiding processed
foods and the like. The second diet was
the Mediterranean diet. Low in simple
carbohydrates, full of vegetables, fish,
and replacing beef and lamb with
chicken. They also consumed walnuts
every day and the diet was calorically
restricted unlike the HDG. Finally, the
third group consumed the same
Mediterranean diet with all the same
parameters but also included daily green
tea and a wolfia globosa or duckweed
shake at dinner generally in replacement
of the other protein sources. This diet
group goes by the street name of green
med. Also, all diet groups underwent
basic physical activity sessions as
well. If you recognize uh some of this,
it might be because we covered another
analysis that included these diets
looking at visceral fat. Anyway, an
important note is that there were no
differences at baseline. So, whatever
results that we see on the brain would
be due to the interventions. I'd also
add that the researchers cleverly added
a genetic screen for a potent
Alzheimer's gene, the APOE4 gene, to
make sure that one group didn't have
greater risk from a genetic perspective.
Again, all of this was equal across the
groups. So, now let's speak a little bit
on brain atrophy or as I very
scientifically put it, brain shrinkage.
These data indicate hawk and when not
pronounced with a frog in your throat ho
which represents hippocample occupancy
score or the density of the section of
your brain called the hippocampus. It is
known to predict cognitive decline. So
as hawk goes down cognitive decline risk
is increased. We see age on the
horizontal axis and we see hawk score on
the vertical. Remember, higher is
better. The individual points are all
the participants of the study,
regardless of diet condition. We can see
that HOC, I promise I won't do hawk
anymore, remains stable or slightly
improves into our 40s, but then it
begins dropping around age 50 and then
like lobbing a ball, it continues to
decline. Again, that decline would
predict an increase in cognitive
impairment. The researchers also report
another metric called LVV or lateral
ventricular volume. But considering LVV
is included in HOC calculations and the
trends are very similar in that data,
I'm going to focus exclusively on HOC.
Just an FYI. In fact, I can show you
what that stuff looks like over the 18
months of the study. Here we're looking
at MRI images of a brain under 50 years
old and a brain over 50 years old. And
the red is the lateral ventricular
volume and the blue is the hippocample
volume. If the ventricular volume
increases, that's bad. And if the
hippocample volume decreases, that's
bad. We can identify increasing and
decreasing by the color and the richness
of the color. Blue is shrinking and red
is enlarging with deeper colors
indicating greater effect. The average
measurements are on the right for the
HOC. We can see clearly that the things
don't change much before 50 and then
there's a significant worsening over the
year and a half for those over age 50.
Okay, so you hit 50, your brain is now
at risk of shriveling up like a prune.
I'll get there too someday. But this
video isn't a doomsday video because
there's something to be done. Let's look
at hope in the face of despair like the
light of alendial. If you got that
reference, let me know. Now, enter the
diets. A reminder, the HDG is the
healthy dietary guidelines diet. The med
or me is the regular Mediterranean diet.
In the green med is the same
Mediterranean diet including the two
foods or substances green tea and monkai
or wolfia
globosa also known as duckweed also
known as wolfia globosa. It's just kind
of all over the place. If the bars move
down and have an asterisk that indicates
a statistically significant worsening of
the HOC measure that we've been focused
on. The only condition that did not show
a worsening was the Mediterranean diet
with the additional foods, but were less
interested in the total sample and more
interested in the data for those who are
50 and older. So, the researchers
extracted the data for just these
individuals, which might offer some
clarity. In that subanalysis, we see
that all three diets experienced some
worsening. Both Mediterranean diets were
superior to the general diet guidelines,
although neither was better than the
other. I will add real quick that there
were some slight advantages to the green
med diet in other outcomes. That all
shown, let's get into three of the
factors that the researchers teased out
from the Mediterranean diets. Before
that, I'm going to be covering some more
on this study in the extended version of
this video that you're currently
watching, which as you long know, if
you're a regular Physionic viewer, is
included with the Physionic Insiders
along with access to all my analyses.
And guess what? There's now a new perk,
live sessions with me. That's right. If
you're a Physionic Insider, you also now
have access to live sessions with me
where we can discuss this study and so
much more. Not to mention the monthly
podcast, the premium email list,
research reviews, videos, and more. It's
a steal, I tell you. Anyway, the link is
in the description if you're interested.
Among the piles of data, there are three
factors that the researchers deemed
important enough to spell out as being
highly associated with these brain
atrophy preventing effects. Here they
are. The factors are walnuts, green tea,
and the monkeyai that we've been
discussing before. The researchers are
again measuring HOC, but we're comparing
three different tiles of consumption.
So, low, medium, and high consumption of
each. In every instance, consuming more
of each was associated with greater
prevention of brain atrophy or shrinkage
than consuming less. There's even a
small chance it'll prevent me from
telling you more bad jokes.
Unfortunately, it was statistically not
significant. So, overall, this data
informs us of several things. One, a
Mediterranean diet, including an energy
deficit and general physical activity
slows down brain shrinkage. Two, the
same Mediterranean diet and conditions
including green tea and monkai might
provide ever so slightly better results
ever so slightly. Three, regardless,
walnut, green tea, and monkeyai
consumption associated with protection
from brain shrinkage. If you'd like more
from this study on other areas of
health, check out this following video.
And if you're interested in other
molecules to protect your brain, check
out this video right here. Both will be
linked in the description, too. See you
over there.
[Music]